<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>SGU - 标签 - 寸方斋</title><link>https://example.com/tags/sgu/</link><description>SGU - 标签 - 寸方斋</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>zh-CN</language><managingEditor>suda.ivywk@gmail.com (Kai Wang)</managingEditor><webMaster>suda.ivywk@gmail.com (Kai Wang)</webMaster><copyright>本作品采用知识共享署名-非商业性使用-相同方式共享 4.0 国际许可协议进行许可</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2015 20:46:00 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://example.com/tags/sgu/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>SGU 144 - Meeting</title><link>https://example.com/2015/07/sgu-144-meeting/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2015 20:46:00 +0800</pubDate><author>作者</author><guid>https://example.com/2015/07/sgu-144-meeting/</guid><description>Description Two of the three members of the winning team of one of the ACM regional contests are going to meet in order to train for the upcoming World Finals. They decided that they will meet sometime between $X$ o&amp;rsquo;clock and $Y$ o&amp;rsquo;clock. Because they never get anywhere on time (they were late even on the day of the regional contest), they did not set an exact time when they</description></item><item><title>SGU 116 - Index of super-prime</title><link>https://example.com/2015/07/sgu-116-index-of-super-prime/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2015 13:39:00 +0800</pubDate><author>作者</author><guid>https://example.com/2015/07/sgu-116-index-of-super-prime/</guid><description>Description Let $P_1, P_2,\cdots ,P_N,\cdots$ be a sequence of prime numbers. Super-prime number is such a prime number that its current number in prime numbers sequence is a prime number too. For example, 3 is a super-prime number, but 7 is not. Index of super-prime for number is 0 iff it is impossible to present it as a sum of few (maybe one) super-prime numbers, and if such presentation exists,</description></item><item><title>SGU 114 - Telecasting station</title><link>https://example.com/2015/03/sgu-114-telecasting-station/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Mar 2015 19:37:00 +0800</pubDate><author>作者</author><guid>https://example.com/2015/03/sgu-114-telecasting-station/</guid><description>Description Every city in Berland is situated on $Ox$ axis. The government of the country decided to build new telecasting station. After many experiments Berland scientists came to a conclusion that in any city citizens displeasure is equal to product of citizens amount in it by distance between city and TV-station. Find such point on $Ox$ axis for station so that sum of displeasures of all cities is minimal. Input</description></item><item><title>SGU 222 - Little Rooks</title><link>https://example.com/2015/03/sgu-222-little-rooks/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Mar 2015 14:26:00 +0800</pubDate><author>作者</author><guid>https://example.com/2015/03/sgu-222-little-rooks/</guid><description>Description Inspired by a &amp;ldquo;Little Bishops&amp;rdquo; problem, Petya now wants to solve problem for rooks. A rook is a piece used in the game of chess which is played on a board of square grids. A rook can only move horizontally and vertically from its current position and two rooks attack each other if one is on the path of the other. Given two numbers $n$ and $k$, your job</description></item><item><title>SGU 154 - Factorial</title><link>https://example.com/2015/03/sgu-154-factorial/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Mar 2015 13:18:00 +0800</pubDate><author>作者</author><guid>https://example.com/2015/03/sgu-154-factorial/</guid><description>Description You task is to find minimal natural number $N$, so that $N!$ contains exactly $Q$ zeroes on the trail in decimal notation. As you know $N! = 1\cdot2\cdots N$. For example, $5! = 120$, 120 contains one zero on the trail. Input One number $Q$ written in the input ($0\leq Q\leq 10^8$). Output Write &amp;ldquo;No solution&amp;rdquo;, if there is no such number $N$, and $N$ otherwise. Sample Input 1</description></item><item><title>SGU 130 - Circle</title><link>https://example.com/2015/03/sgu-130-circle/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Mar 2015 11:04:00 +0800</pubDate><author>作者</author><guid>https://example.com/2015/03/sgu-130-circle/</guid><description>Description On a circle border there are $2k$ different points $A_1, A_2, \cdots , A_{2k}$, located contiguously. These points connect $k$ chords so that each of points $A_1, A_2, \cdots, A_{2k}$ is the end point of one chord. Chords divide the circle into parts. You have to find $N$ - the number of different ways to connect the points so that the circle is broken into minimal possible amount of</description></item><item><title>SGU 276 - Andrew's Troubles</title><link>https://example.com/2015/03/sgu-276-andrews-troubles/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Mar 2015 09:48:00 +0800</pubDate><author>作者</author><guid>https://example.com/2015/03/sgu-276-andrews-troubles/</guid><description>Description Famous Berland ACM-ICPC team Anisovka consists of three programmers: Andrew, Michael and Ilya. A long time ago, during the first few months the team was founded, Andrew was very often late to the trainings and contests. To stimulate Andrew to be more punctual, Ilya and Andrew decided to introduce a new rule for team participants. If somebody is late (i.e. comes at least one second after appointed time) he</description></item><item><title>SGU 126 - Boxes</title><link>https://example.com/2015/03/sgu-126-boxes/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Mar 2015 09:28:00 +0800</pubDate><author>作者</author><guid>https://example.com/2015/03/sgu-126-boxes/</guid><description>Description There are two boxes. There are $A$ balls in the first box, and $B$ balls in the second box ($0 &amp;lt; A + B &amp;lt; 2147483648$). It is possible to move balls from one box to another. From one box into another one should move as many balls as the other box already contains. You have to determine, whether it is possible to move all balls into one box.</description></item><item><title>SGU 118 - Digital Root</title><link>https://example.com/2015/02/sgu-118-digital-root/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2015 15:18:00 +0800</pubDate><author>作者</author><guid>https://example.com/2015/02/sgu-118-digital-root/</guid><description>Description Let $f(n)$ be a sum of digits for positive integer $n$. If $f(n)$ is one-digit number then it is a digital root for $n$ and otherwise digital root of $n$ is equal to digital root of $f(n)$. For example, digital root of 987 is 6. Your task is to find digital root for expression $$ A_1\cdot A_2\cdots A_N + A_1\cdot A_2\cdots A_{N-1} + \cdots + A_1\cdot A_2 + A_1$$</description></item><item><title>SGU 117 - Counting</title><link>https://example.com/2015/02/sgu-117-counting/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2015 14:14:00 +0800</pubDate><author>作者</author><guid>https://example.com/2015/02/sgu-117-counting/</guid><description>Description Find amount of numbers for given sequence of integer numbers such that after raising them to the $M$-th power they will be divided by $K$. Input Input consists of two lines. There are three integer numbers $N, M, K$ ($0&amp;lt;N, M, K&amp;lt;10001$) on the first line. There are N positive integer numbers − given sequence (each number is not more than 10001) − on the second line. Output Write</description></item></channel></rss>